David R. Saeva

drsaeva@gmail.com • (585) 261-5771 • drsaeva.github.io • Baltimore, MD 21201

SUMMARY

Node, is developer experienced building cloud-native RESTful applications. At home in an AGILE, DevOps environment.

TOOLBOX

Frontend: JavaScript ES6 ● HTML/CSS/SASS ● React.js ● Angular 1.x/2+ ● TypeScript

API: REST/SOAP • Node.js • Express.js • Java • Spring/Spring Boot

Data Layer: PostgreSQL ● PL/SQL

Testing: Protractor/Cucumber • Jasmine/Karma • Mocha/Chai • JUnit/Mockito

Scripting: Python • Groovy • Bash • Perl

DevOps: Bitbucket • Github • Docker • Jenkins • Amazon Web Services • Azure

Environments: Red Hat Linux • OS X • Windows

Power Skills: Creativity ● Problem Solving ● Assertiveness ● AGILE ● Technical Communication

RELEVANT EMPLOYMENT AND EXPERIENCE

Peraton (Northrop Grumman Heritage) Northrop Grumman, Woodlawn, MD — Principal Software Development Analyst

MAY 2019 - PRESENT

Backend Node.js developer on a project with a federal agency to implement a disability benefits administration system. Member of a large team in a DevOps environment using an AGILE methodology, focusing on meeting a tight feature release deadline while modernizing the existing code base to ES6 standards.

- Rewrote a callback-driven REST application stack that resides in AWS using Express.js, knex.js, and PostgreSQL to
 leverage ES6 promises, async/await, and modularized architecture, routing, and logging practices. Collaborated on
 refactoring efforts up through the major release of this rewrite. Implemented new REST API routes for business needs.
- Developed modularized presentation layer code using **HTML**, **Sass**, **Handlebars.js**, and **ES6** to be ultimately served as PDFs via **Express.js** and **Puppeteer** to a distributed, national client base numbering in the millions of users
- Developed a task/project management suite for internal usage in **React.js**, with a containerized **Node.js** backend and a managed **PostgreSQL** instance. Hosted in **Azure**, leveraging **Azure** AD for authentication and session management.
- Collaborated in an Agile team environment with dozens of stakeholders and a nation-wide user base scaling to millions..

$\textbf{Capital One Financial Corporation,} \ \texttt{McLean, VA} - \textit{Software Developer}$

JULY 2018 - MAY 2019

Full-stack Java 8 and Node.js developer on a team of six in a mature DevOps environment using an AGILE methodology. Development efforts focused on feature releases and paying down existing technical debt to improve our team's release SLA.

- Designed and implemented a pattern for refactoring my team's Node.js REST API Microservice to componentize the
 existing code base. Implemented a new SOAP call to a downstream dependency leveraging this pattern. Lead a larger
 refactoring effort for the remaining SOAP calls in this API, coordinating with three other teammates and serving as the
 primary point-of-contact on this effort for management.
- Refactored a **REST API Microservice** written in **Java 8** leveraging **Spring** from **SSL** to **OAuth2**-based authentication. Further refactored the same application to sunset a vendor API in favor of an in-house managed resource. Developed a POC refactor for that same API in **Node.js**, **Typescript**, and **Nest.js**.
- Wrote a command-line app in **Node.js** and **TypeScript** to enable reliable, transactional updates to the properties file to enable a 1-day SLA for updates to the file, a vast improvement over the vendor's 3-week SLA for similar DB changes.

Architected a strategy for migrating the property file to AWS S3, including secure retrieval, updates via AWS Lambda, and a POC UI in Angular 6 that would enable file updates to be performed by product owners.

- Updated existing Jenkins pipelines and infrastructure configuration—as—code to reduce boilerplate and improve
 maintainability. Enabled daytime live releases to the production environment. Performed pipeline—managed continuous
 deployment releases of Docker containers across all environments in AWS to cloud architecture leveraging Route 53, S3,
 EC2, and ECS.
- Wrote automation tests for an **Angular.js** frontend with **TypeScript**, **Protractor**, and **Cucumber** for my team's feature. Implemented and released UI updates to the same frontend feature as directed by product owners.
- Provided support, troubleshooting, and issue resolution for all consumers of my team's feature across all environments using CloudWatch, SNS, Splunk, and other utilities.
- Collaborated in an Agile team environment.

Revature LLC, Reston, VA — *Software Developer*

FEBRUARY 2018 - MAY 2019

Trained and employed as a full stack software developer specializing in development of **RESTful applications** and **microservices** for enterprise clients.

- Trained in a variety of full stack technologies specific to enterprise software development, including Java 8, Spring/Spring
 Boot, Microservices, Amazon Web Services, REST, TypeScript, Angular 5, PL/SQL, JavaScript ES 6, JUnit/Mockito,
 Jasmine/Karma, Pivotal Cloud Foundry, and Jenkins.
- Engineered a Microservice ecosystem in Java 8 leveraging Netflix OSS (Zuul, Hystrix, Eureka) and Kafka MQ from an
 existing monolith and integrated it into an Angular 5 frontend.
- Developed a full-stack web application in Java 8, Angular 5, and PL/SQL hosted on AWS in a VPC environment using EC2 and RDS
- Collaborated in an Agile team environment

Cubix Health Technologies, Baltimore, MD — *Developer*

NOVEMBER 2016 - MAY 2017

Development in **Python** for a medical visualization technology startup using machine learning as a member of a small team.

Johns Hopkins University AAP, Baltimore, MD — *Graduate Student*

MAY 2016 - AUGUST 2017

Engaged in graduate coursework in computer science (bioinformatics). Completed several projects, including:

R: statistical analyses of gene expression in sleep apnea patients using machine learning

Full stack development with HTML5 and JS: bacterial gene search engine, force-directed graph of an ontology

Object-oriented programming in Java 8 and Python: sorting algorithms, data structures, trees, basic UIs

Maryland DHMH, Baltimore, MD — Data Entry Operator

MAY 2016 - NOVEMBER 2016

QA and manual entry of HIV patient records against state database. Developed a **Java** application to automate an existing data entry workflow with the intent to reduce manual operator workload by 10%:

Designed file-driven I/O flow to parse scanned HIV medical records Parsed data from scanned reports using optical character recognition Automated entry of data into existing frontend with **Selenium**

Regularly discussed project requirements and progress with non-technical supervisors.

University of Maryland Baltimore, MD — Graduate Research Assistant in Biochemistry

JULY 2014 - OCTOBER 2015

Engaged in independent research and coordinated efforts with colleagues. Developed a series of Perl scripts:

Cross-referenced data from cancer gene expression databases to find matching genes in lymphoma studies Identified matching genes containing sequences (strings) closely matching a sequence of interest Pushed data to and from an ad-hoc SQL database, using it to guide experiments in the wet laboratory

Regularly discussed progress on projects, including lay summaries of code, with supervisors and collaborators.

EDUCATION

JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY **UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND SUNY COLLEGE AT BROCKPORT** • Brockport, NY (*May '14*) **SUNY PURCHASE COLLEGE**

- Baltimore, MD (Aug '17)
- Baltimore, MD (*Oct '15*)
- Purchase, NY (May '10)
- Graduate coursework in Bioinformatics
- Graduate coursework in Biochemistry
- Bachelor of Science in Biochemistry
- Bachelor of Music in Performance